Charles Coiner Papers
Charles Coiner Papers
1933-1984
Coiner, Charles T.
10 linear ft.
Correspondence (1930s-1970); design drawings for government commissions, including preliminary sketches and other material pertaining to the NRA blue eagle as well as civilian defense logos and war posters; documents relating to various Ayer clients, including the Container Corporation of America; ms. essays and speeches, and tear sheets for Coiner's 'Clipping Board' column; and memorabilia, including awards, clippings, exhibition catalogs, and photographs. Correspondence includes letters of Raymond A. Ballinger, Herbert Bayer, Harry Bouras, Alexey Brodovitch, Werner Drewes, Leo Lionni, George Samerjan, Lajos Szalay, and others.
150109
Biographical History
Charles Coiner (1897-1989) was an American painter and art director. He joined the advertising firm of N.W. Ayer & Sons in 1924 as a layout designer, became art director in 1929, and was a vice-president when he retired in 1964. Coiner designed civilian defense and government posters during World War II, the blue eagle symbol of the National Recovery Administration, and the Boys Clubs of America commemorative stamp issued in 1960.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1933 to 1984, the Charles Coiner Papers comprises correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the American painter and advertising agency art director (1897-1989). A reflection of both his 40-year association with N. W. Ayer and his commissioned work for the government, the collection illuminates not only Coiner's pioneering efforts to bring artists without commercial experience to advertising, but also his creative work as a designer of war posters, civilian defense logos, and the Blue Eagle symbol of the National Recovery Administration.
Encompassing both incoming letters and outgoing carbons and/or drafts, the Correspondence (Box 1) focuses primarily on Coiner's work with Ayer Inc., a career which began in 1924 in layout design and ended with his 1964 retirement as art director and vice-president. Although there are some letters from the 1930s in response to the publicity surrounding Coiner's Blue Eagle design, the bulk of the correspondence centers around the 1950s and '60s and concerns advertising campaigns for various clients, most notably the Container Corporation of America. An active recruiter of artists for his advertising projects, Coiner's correspondents include Tore Asplund, Raymond A. Ballinger, Herbert Bayer, Harry Bouras, Alexey Brodovitch, Bob Cargill, Werner Drewes, W. Emerton Heitland, Harry Leith-Ross, Antonio Martino, Louise Pershing, George Samerjan, James William Schucker, Joseph Sinel, Kenneth Stuart, Lajos Szalay, Norman Todhunter, and Hugo Weber.
Designs, drawings, personal greeting cards, and printed reproductions of paintings constitute Artwork (Boxes 1-2). Arranged by client, artwork designs include original sketches and/or printed examples of logos, trademarks, letterheads, stationery, and posters which Coiner produced for both private companies and the federal government. All stages of development from original sketches to a full-size banner document the creation of Coiner's NRA Blue Eagle and its ubiquitous display. Other government commissions included posters and logos designed for the Office for Emergency Management, the Office of Production Management, and the Office of Civilian Defense as well as a 4-cent Boys' Clubs of America commemorative stamp for the Post Office.
Writings includes manuscript essays, printed articles, and the text of a number of Coiner's speeches delivered between 1946 and 1962. With the exception of the tear sheets for his "Clipping Board" columns (1944-1966) from Advertising Agency Magazine, Coiner's manuscript essays and published articles have been arranged by title in a single sequence.
Memorabilia consists of awards, photographs, and printed material, which includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs (1963-1984), and news releases. Magazine reproductions of and articles about the NRA Blue Eagle constitute the bulk of the clippings.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Ballinger, Raymond A., 1907-1985.; Bayer, Herbert, 1900-1985.; Bouras, Harry.; Brodovitch, Alexey, 1898-1971.; Coiner, Charles T.; Drewes, Werner, 1899-1985.; Lionni, Leo, 1910-1999.; Samerjan, George.; Szalay, Lajos, 1909-1995.; Container Corporation of America.; N. W. Ayer & Sons.; United States. -- National Recovery Administration.; United States. -- Office for Emergency Management; Advertising agencies -- United States.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Art and industry.; Art and war.; Commercial art -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Design drawings.; Exhibition catalogs.; Freehand drawings (drawings); Monoprints (painting and printing works); Photographs.; Posters.; Speeches (documents); Artists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Charles Coiner.
Inventory
- Biographical Material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Coiner to Elsie Mae Howe, 1924 (Box 1)
  - Coiner to Elsie Mae Howe, about recital, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930s-1986; undated; 10 folders (Box 1)
    See also Selected Index to Correpondence for more information.
- Artwork
  - Designs (by client), most of these are examples of print advertisements; almost none is original artwork
    - AT & T, 1960-1962; "Telephone location identification" (Box 2)
    - Avisco (textiles), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Avondale (textiles), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Boeing, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Buckingham Township Civic Association, undated (Box 2)
    - Champion Papers (Miho), undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Community Chests and Councils, Inc., 1945 (Box 2)
    - C & P Telephone, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Camel (cigarettes), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Capehart and Farnsworth (audio cabinets), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Champ (wool), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Container Corporation of America
      - [General], 1945-1964; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - Oversize material, 1960; undated (Oversize 3)
    - Crown (rayon), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Dole (fruit), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Ekco (kitchen appliances), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Felt & Tarrant (calculators, "Comptometers"; also at least one ad for war bonds), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Ford Motor Company, sketches, layouts, printed advertisements, etc. for Lincoln Symphony, Ford V-8, Murray bodies (Oversize 2)
    - Great Abaco Club, undated (Box 2)
    - Forstmann (wool), undated (Oversize 2)
    - French Line (cruise company), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Goodyear, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Hawaiian Pineapple Company, Ltd., 1947 (Box 2)
    - Kelly-Springfield (tires), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Ladies Home Journal, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Marcus & Company (jewellers), undated (Oversize 2)
    - National War Fund, 1943 (Box 2)
    - N. W. Ayers (advertising agency), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Octagon Soap Products, undated (Box 2)
    - Pennsylvania Hospital, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Pharmaceutical Manufacturers Association, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Philadelphia Museum of Art, undated (Box 2)
    - Plymouth (Chrysler), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Polk-Miller (canine medication; ad relates to supporting armed forces), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Punch, undated (Oversize 2)
    - Silvercup (bread), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Steinway (pianos), undated (Oversize 2)
    - United Air Lines, undated (Oversize 2)
    - U.S. Government
      - National Recovery Administration (NRA), 1933
        - [General], 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Posters, 1933-1934; undated; several different designs, including humorous ones "For Communists" and "For burlesque and circus fans" (Oversize 3)
        - Banner [?], canvas, red white and blue, VERY large when unfolded (Oversize 4)
      - Office for Emergency Management, 1942
        See also War Production Board.
        - [General] (Box 2)
        - [General], 9 items, some duplicates (Map-case 132)
      - Office of Civilian Defense, 1941
        - [General], 3 folders (Box 2)
        - Icons and symbols, for air raid warden, emergency housing, medical facility, etc.; original art (Oversize 3)
      - Office of Production Management
        - [General], undated (Box 3)
        - Posters, undated (Oversize xxx)
      - Post Office, 1960; 4 cent Boys' Clubs of America commemorative postage stamp (Box 3)
      - U.S.S. Enterprise, 1961 (Box 3)
      - War Manpower Commission, undated (Box 3)
      - War Production Board, 1943
        See also Office for Emergency Management.
        - [General] (Box 3)
        - [General] (Map-case 132)
    - Waltham (watches), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Wamsutta (sheets, pillowcases), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Webster (cigars), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Yardley (perfumes / fragrances), undated (Oversize 2)
    - Miscellaneous, assorted letterheads, stationery, trademarks, etc. (Box 3)
  - Non-client or unidentified
    - Calendars with reproductions of Coiner art, 1973-1974; 1980 (Box 3)
    - Drawings, original artwork including drawings, sketches, etc. (Box 3)
    - Drawings, oversize, original artwork including drawings, sketches, etc. (Oversize 5)
    - Greeting cards, personal, 1969-1970; undated (Box 3)
    - Paintings, printed reproductions (Box 3)
    - Prints, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Prints, oversize (Oversize 5)
    - Prints, oversize (Map-case 132)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - "Clipping Board", 1944-1956; undated; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - "Clipping Board", enlargements used in Philadelphia Museum College of Art exhibition (Oversize 1)
    - Miscellaneous
      - By title A-Z, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Untitled (Box 4)
  - Panel discussion, Art Directors Club, on “Changing Role of the Art Director", 9 Oct 1959; coiner_c_001; 1 reel tape, 7" (Box 8)
  - Speeches, 1946-1962; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards
    - Art Directors Club of Philadephia Hall of Fame, 1973 (Oversize 6)
    - Art Directors Club of Philadephia Hall of Fame, undated (Oversize 6)
    - Audubon Artists 40th Annual Exhibit Grumbacher Art Award, 1982 (Oversize 6)
    - Ayer Centennial 25-Year Club, 1969 (Oversize 6)
    - Bucks County Arts Award, 1982 (Oversize 6)
    - Philadelphia Club of Advertising Woman, 1961 (Oversize 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1949-1969 (Box 5)
  - Financial, 1962-1975; undated (Box 5)
  - Inventories of paintings, 1981-1985; undated (Box 5)
  - Legal, 1963; undated (Box 5)
  - Medical, 1953-1974; undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Photograph, oversize, unidentified commencement ceremony (Oversize 3)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings
      - NRA Blue Eagle, 1933-1935; undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, 1933-1989; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Exhibition announcements, invitations, 1960s-1980s; undated; 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1920s-1960s; undated; 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1970s-1980s; undated; 5 folders (Box 7)
    - News releases (Box 7)
    - Typography (Box 7)
    - Wartime images, majority World War II (Box 7)
  - Scrapbook, bound volume containing clipped monograms, seals, wax seals, etc. (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Audiorecording
    - Art Directors Club Panel Discussion - “Changing Role of the Art Director, 10/09/1959; coiner_c_001; running time 90:00 minutes; 1/4 inch audio tape (Box 8)
Selected Index to Correspondence
Anderson, Cal 1963 Sept. 20
Anderson, Robert O. 1966 Apr. 14 1969 July 29
Asplund, Tore 1963 Feb. 28
Ballinger, Raymond A. 1967 Mar. 9
Banbery, Fred E. 1962 Oct. 30 1963 May 14
Barnes, Clara Ernest 1962 Feb. 5 1962 Feb, 8 (outgoing)
Bayer, Herbert 1962 Jan. 30 (outgoing) 1962 Jan. 31 (outgoing) 1962 Feb. 6 1962 Feb. 9 (outgoing) 1962 Feb. 15 1962 Mar. 2 (outgoing) 1962 May 10 (outgoing) 1962 Apr. 27 (outgoing) 1962 June 11 (outgoing) 1962 Dec. 17 (copy of letter to Clark Richert) 1962 Dec. 27 (outgoing) 1963 Feb. 4 (outgoing) 1963 Apr. 18 (outgoing) 1963 May 23 (outgoing) 1963 May 28 (outgoing) 1963 June 3 1963 June 12 (outgoing) 1963 July 16 (outgoing)
Beall, Lester 1962 Oct. 10 1962 Oct. 23 (outgoing)
Berko, Ferenc 1962 Aug. 3 1962 Oct. 12 (outgoing) 1962 Nov. 20
Bouras, Harry 1962 Jan. 15 (outgoing) 1962 Jan. 26 (outgoing) 1962 Feb. 2 (outgoing)
Brattinga, Peter 1962 June 6 1962 June 20 (outgoing) 1962 Sept. 17 1962 Nov. 5 (outgoing) 1963 May 6 1963 May 22
Briggs, Austin 1963 Aug. 15
Brodovitch, Alexey 1956 June 14 1962 July 13 1962 Oct. 25 (outgoing) 1963 June 17 1963 June 19 (outgoing) 1963 June 22 1963 June 24 (outgoing) 1963 July 9
Cargill, Bob 1963 Oct. 3
Deskey, Donald 1962 Feb. 8 (outgoing)
Drewes, Werner 1962 Feb. 20 (outgoing) 1962 Feb. 25 1962 Mar. 14 (outgoing)
Dreyfuss, Henry 1962 June 18 1962 July 13 (outgoing)
Elton, Wallace 1962 Aug. 30 1962 Oct. 12 (outgoing)
Gingrich, Arnold 1962 Oct. 12 (outgoing) 1962 Oct. 15 1963 Apr. 18 (outgoing) 1963 Apr. 19 1963 Apr. 24 1963 May 14 (outgoing) 1963 May 15 1963 June 11 1963 June 13 (outgoing) 1963 June 14 1963 Oct. 4 (outgoing) 1971 Feb. 26 (outgoing)
Guyatt, Richard 1962 Mar. 24 1962 June 15 (outgoing) 1962 July 13 (outgoing) 1962 Nov. 7 1962 Dec. 19 (outgoing)
Heitland, W. Emerton 1963 Feb. 27
Leith-Ross, Harry 1963 Feb. 20
Lionni, Leo 1962 Feb. 28 (outgoing) 1962 Mar. 13
Martino, Antonio 1963 Feb. 21
Mednick, Sol 1962 Oct. 30 (outgoing)
Michener, James A. 1962 Feb. 20 (outgoing)
Miho, James N. 1962 Jan. 30 (outgoing to Herbert Bayer)
Pershing, Louise 1963 Aug. 5 1963 Oct. 3 (outgoing) 1963 Oct. 8
Pullen, John J. 1963 Aug. 22
Remington, Roger R. 1985 Sept. 6 1985 Nov. 27 1986 Jan. 18
Samerjan, George 1963 Feb. 26
Schary, Saul 1963 May 29 (outgoing)
Schucker, James William 1962 Jan. 31 1962 Feb. 26 1962 Feb. 28 (outgoing)
Sinel, Joseph 1933 July 28
Small, William Arden 1968 Feb. 19 (outgoing to Midtown Galleries) 1968 Sept. 27 1969 July 21
Stuart, Kenneth 1962 July 10
Szalay, Lajos 1962 Feb. 10 1962 Feb. 12 (outgoing)
Thompson, Bradbury 1963 Jan. 7 (outgoing)
Thon, William 1967 Dec.
Todhunter, Norman 1962 Feb. 22 1962 Feb. 23 (outgoing) 1962 Feb. 25 1962 Mar. 2 (outgoing) 1962 Mar. 6
United States National Recovery Administration 1933 Sept. 6 1934 Aug. 11 (2) 1934 Oct. 13
Weber, Hugo 1963 May 7
Zerbe, Karl 1963 Jan. 2 (outgoing)